<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Shahid Hasan Munzur | Jubayer Hossain</title>
    <link>https://hossainlab.github.io/authors/shahid-hasan-munzur/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://hossainlab.github.io/authors/shahid-hasan-munzur/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Shahid Hasan Munzur</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Jubayer Hossain</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 06:41:30 +0600</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://hossainlab.github.io/img/headers/canyon.jpg</url>
      <title>Shahid Hasan Munzur</title>
      <link>https://hossainlab.github.io/authors/shahid-hasan-munzur/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self Management And Knowledge of Diabetic Patients in Bangladesh and the Prevalence rate of Diabetes</title>
      <link>https://hossainlab.github.io/publication/self-management-of-diabetes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 06:41:30 +0600</pubDate>
      <guid>https://hossainlab.github.io/publication/self-management-of-diabetes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diabetes mellitus is associated with significant morbidity and mortality in Bangladesh, where healthcare facilities and accessibility are inadequate. Diabetes is also linked to heart disease, stroke, and kidney failure. The secret to achieving clinical goals in ambulatory treatment is assumed to be sufficient patient awareness of self-care.
In Bangladesh, there are a few studies on the relationship between awareness and self-care practices among type 2 diabetes patients, but none are recent. Despite this, little research has been done on type 1 diabetes patients&amp;rsquo; self-care habits and awareness.The foundation of DM management is diabetes education combined with adequate motivation of patients and caregivers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objectives&#34;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since many people with diabetes are uncertain if they have Type 1 or Type2, the questionnaire included four questions to help determine the most likely type&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this study was to see if there was a connection between diabetes awareness and self-care practices among Type 1 and Type 2 diabetes patients&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estimate the proportion of respondents with diabetes type by these questions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;survey&#34;&gt;Survey&lt;/h2&gt;
 &lt;iframe
       src=&#34;https://forms.gle/zSRnUekXswLKqDp17&#34;
       width=&#34;100%&#34;
       height=&#34;1000px&#34;
       style=&#34;border:none;&#34;&gt;
 &lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
