<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bioinformatics | Jubayer Hossain</title>
    <link>https://hossainlab.github.io/categories/bioinformatics/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://hossainlab.github.io/categories/bioinformatics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Bioinformatics</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Jubayer Hossain</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://hossainlab.github.io/img/headers/canyon.jpg</url>
      <title>Bioinformatics</title>
      <link>https://hossainlab.github.io/categories/bioinformatics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biocomputing: A New and Quickly Developing Field</title>
      <link>https://hossainlab.github.io/2022/08/04/biocomputing-what-why/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://hossainlab.github.io/2022/08/04/biocomputing-what-why/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Do you enjoy maths and biology? Do you enjoy writing code? Then focus on biocomputing, the career of the future that will give you a variety of job options. In this article, I will discuss what biocomputing is and why we should learn these skills in the modern day. In particular, students with a life science background should learn the biocomputing workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-is-biocomputing&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What is Biocomputing?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biocomputing is an innovative branch of technology that functions at the interface of biology, engineering, and computer science. It tries to employ cells or their subcomponent molecules (such as DNA or RNA) to do activities normally performed by a computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;features-of-biocomputing&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Features of Biocomputing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biocomputing (Bioinformatics) is placed at the intersection of Medicine, Biology, Applied Mathematics, and Computer Science. Those who have chosen this career are responsible for addressing global issues such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Search for methods of treatment of cancer, chronic and autoimmune diseases;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Extending the life of the population, improving the ecological situation and searching for the longevity genome;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Development, planning, implementation of mathematical methods, algorithms and programs used for the analysis of medical and biological information;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Application of the obtained research and practice results.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;why-biocomputing&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Why Biocomputing?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern diagnostic and research techniques have led to a growth in the quantity of scientific data, which is extremely difficult to manually process. In this instance, Biocomputing (Bioinformatics) is of assistance. In the second part of the 20th century, it emerged as an interdisciplinary science. Biocomputing incorporates components of applied mathematics, statistics, computer science, mathematical and computer modeling, and programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The field is new and expanding rapidly, and it will continue to do so in the future since the use of computer methods assures great accuracy, speed, and eliminates the human element. There is a demand for biocomputing technology in biochemistry, molecular biology, microbiology, pharmacy,biophysics, ecology, pharmacology, agriculture, and genetics, among other fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;advantages-of-biocomputing&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Advantages of Biocomputing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;All options are open to Biocomputing professionals, from local research institutions to reputable worldwide IT firms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Biocomputing specialists do not engage directly with patients or biological material, as their work involves mathematical methodologies and computer systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Knowledge of programming languages and the fundamentals of applied mathematics enables Biocomputing professionals to quickly transition to other fields, such as traditional programming, genomic data science, software development, and testing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Continuous self-development and improvement of professional skills.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ability to analyze data sets, knowing that the results of work in the long term will save the lives of thousands of people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;some-major-courses-in-biocomputing&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Some Major Courses in Biocomputing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction to Life Sciences &amp;amp; Bioinformatics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applied Mathematics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web programming and Databases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bioinformatics Lab I&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bioinformatics Lab II&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction to Programming Languages (Python, R, and Julia)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fundamentals of Biostatistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Science: Introduction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Machine Learning (Artificial Intelligence)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;leading-positions-in-biocomputing&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Leading Positions in Biocomputing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Analyst&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bioinformatician&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bioinformatics Scientist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Scientist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are working on designing a biocomputing program at CHIRAL Bangladesh. Next, I will share how you can start learning biocomputing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
